Guide to the Montgomery Hare Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Montgomery Hare papers
1908-1996
YCAL MSS 246
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.11
(27 boxes) + 2 record storage boxes, and 1 broadside folder
The collection consists of writings, notebooks and sketchbooks, correspondence, personal files, theater files, and audio material, and documents Hare's work as a playwright, producer, and director, and his work in other literary genres.
Hare, Montgomery
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Montgomery Hare Papers were donated by Patrick H. Hare in 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
MONTGOMERY HARE (1911-1998)
Montgomery Hare, 1911-1998, was a playwright, theater producer, and poet. Born in New York City, Hare graduated from Groton School in 1929 and from Yale University in 1933 with honors in literature.
Hare wrote and directed plays for the Barter Theatre in Abingdon, Virginia in the late 1940s, and was also active with the Parsons Theatre and the Penobscot Charitable Trust. His published books of poetry include Three Eagles (1954), To Beat the Air: Poems and Drawings (1964), and Say This of Me (1981). He also wrote novels and his memoirs.
From 1940 on, Hare lived in Cornwall, Connecticut. He was a founder and president of the Housatonic Valley Association, which worked to protect the lands and waters of the Housatonic Watershed.
Scope and Contents
The Montgomery Hare Papers consist of writings, notebooks and sketchbooks, correspondence, personal files, theater files, and audio material. The collection documents Hare's work as a playwright, producer, and director, and his work in other literary genres.
Writings include typescripts and manuscripts of Hare's plays, poems, novels, memoirs, and other writings. Notebooks also contain manuscripts of poems, along with notes, sketches, and drawings. Family correspondence includes letters from Hare to his first wife, Mary (May) Sturges, and letters from Hare to his parents, written while he was away at school. General correspondence includes letters to Hare from writers, friends, and acquaintances, among others, as well as some outgoing correspondence. Personal files include Hare's journals, family papers, and files stemming from his work with the Housatonic Valley Association. Theater files include scripts, correspondence, and other material relating to Hare's work with various theaters, including the Barter Theatre and Parsons Theatre, as well as some theater memorabilia. Audio material includes sound recordings (on reel-to-reel tape and audio cassette) of Hare's work and the work of others, especially dating from the 1950s, and phonograph records containing various sound effects.
American drama -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Theater -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiocassettes; Audiotapes; Sound recordings; Hare, Montgomery; Sturges, Mary; Barter Theatre (Abingdon, Va.); Housatonic Valley Association; Parsons' Theatre (Organization: Hartford, Conn.)
- Writings, Series I
  - Plays
    - "Another Part of the Island" (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - "The At-One-Ment of Christian" (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
    - "Baa-Baa, Black Sheep" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Beautiful, Beautiful" (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Beyond Colonnus" (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - "Cain's-Keep" (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    - "Ceremony for the Coming of Darkness" (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "A Christmas Miracle" (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Command Performance" (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "The Death of Washington" (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - "The Death of Washington" (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
    - "Four One Act Plays" (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - "Gaia", [1990] (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "George Washington" (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Get Thee Behind Me" (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "In the Image of God" (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "The King's Threshold Revisited" (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "Liberty" (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "A Madonna for Americans" (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "Miracle in Brooklyn" (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "The Month is March" (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "My Father's House" (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    - "Oh God, My God" (Box 2, Folder 37-38)
    - "One for the Road" (Box 2, Folder 39-41)
    - "Out of Africa" (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "A Pair of Glasses" (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
    - "Pastoral Call" (Box 3, Folder 45-46)
    - "Pin-Up" (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
    - ["Queen Lear"], 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 49-54)
    - "Rock of Ages" (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "Sailboat in a Cave" (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "Scold" (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "Ship 'A Sailing" (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "Someone Is Missing" (Box 3, Folder 59-60)
    - "There'll Always Be an Empire" (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - "Three Eagles" (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - "Three One-Act Plays" (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "Three Queens" (Box 3, Folder 64-66)
    - "Three To Make Treason" (Box 3, Folder 67-70)
    - "The Time of Day Is Night" (Box 4, Folder 71-72)
    - "Ultima Thule" (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - "Venus Shot" (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - "You Don't Have To Be Dead To Be Perfect" (Box 4, Folder 75-77)
    - [Unidentified plays, related papers] (Box 4, Folder 78-79)
    - [Unidentified plays] (Box 4, Folder 80-82)
  - Novels, poems, essays, and other writings
    Scope and Contents
    See also Other Papers (Box 15).
    - "Apollo"
      - Characters and synopsis (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Added chapters, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - Dream sequences (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - "The Runaways" [treatment and screenplay by Jim Burroughs and Suzanne Bauman] (Box 4, Folder 87)
      - "The River Runners" [treatment and screenplay by Jim Burroughs and Suzanne Bauman] (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - "Swan Song", 1975 (Box 4, Folder 89-91)
      - Original handwritten copy (Box 5, Folder 92-93)
      - Rewrites (Box 5, Folder 94-101)
    - "To Beat the Air," typed copy and original drawings, [1964] (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - "To Beat the Air," original drawings
    - "To Beat the Air," printed plates
    - ["Heaven Scent"] (Box 5, Folder 103-106)
    - "Heaven Scent", 1996 (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - "Heaven Scent", 1996 (Box 6, Folder 108-110)
    - "Say This of Me"
      - Printing information, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 111)
      - Card file (Box 6, Folder 112-114)
      - Errata (Box 6, Folder 115)
      - Orders, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 116-117)
      - Corrections Copy, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 118)
      - Dummies, proofs, and original handwritten poems
    - "Three Eagles"
      - Proofs, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 119)
      - First proofs and corrections (Box 6, Folder 120)
      - [Galleys] (Box 6, Folder 121)
      - [Typescript copy] (Box 6, Folder 122)
      - [Galley proofs] (Box 6, Folder 123-124)
    - April '75, Questionable, so far as publication now is concerned (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - [Illustrated poem ("Whether God is in fact dead...")], 1970 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - Stories, "Puddings", "Sammy", "Mea Culpa", "Zinderneuf Revisited" (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Essays (Box 7, Folder 128)
    - Review of "Synergetics" (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - [Poems] (Box 7, Folder 130)
    - [Notes] (Box 7, Folder 131)
    - Christmas Pageant, Easter Essay, Tribute to Frances Mangravite, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 132)
    - [Miscellaneous] (Box 7, Folder 133-134)
    - [Unidentified writings] (Box 7, Folder 135-136)
    - [Miscellaneous and fragments] (Box 7, Folder 137-139)
    - Poems with drawings
    - Handwritten poem (Box bsd)
  - Memoirs
    - "Scrag, The Story of A Love Affair with an Island", [typescript] (Box 7, Folder 140-142)
    - "Scrag", notes (Box 7, Folder 143)
    - "Scrag", correspondence, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 144)
    - ["Four Letters from Scrag Island, Maine"] (Box 7, Folder 145)
    - Volume III (Box 7, Folder 146-147)
    - "Scrag", [annotated typescript] (Box 7, Folder 148)
    - "Scrag", [manuscript] (Box 7, Folder 149-151)
    - "Scrag", Volume I, original (Box 8, Folder 152-153)
    - "Scrag", Volume II, original (Box 8, Folder 154-156)
    - "Scrag", Volume III (Box 8, Folder 157-158)
    - "Scrag", typescript (Box 8, Folder 159-160)
- Notebooks and sketchbooks, Series II
  - [Notebooks, manuscripts and drawings] (Box 8, Folder 161-166)
  - [Notebook, unidentified writing] (Box 8, Folder 167)
  - [Notebook, The Atonement of Christian] (Box 9, Folder 168)
  - [Sketchbooks] (Box 9, Folder 169)
  - [Sketchbook, "Abram, My Old Man"] (Box 9, Folder 170)
  - [Sketchbooks] (Box 9, Folder 171-173)
  - [Notebook] (Box 9, Folder 174)
  - [Notebooks]
- Printed Music, Series III
  - [Bound volume] (Box 9, Folder 175)
  - [Loose items] (Box 9, Folder 176)
- Correspondence, Series IV
  - Family
    - [Letters to May Sturges], 1934-1938 (Box 9, Folder 177-182)
    - [Letters to May Sturges], 1934-1938 (Box 10, Folder 183-185)
    - [Letters to Mr. and Mrs. Montgomery Hare], 1924-1930 (Box 10, Folder 186-189)
  - General
    - [Correspondence, including letter from Dave Brubeck] (Box 10, Folder 190)
    - Letter to J. D. Fitzhugh, 1953 Jun (Box 10, Folder 191)
    - [Correspondence, outgoing] (Box 10, Folder 192)
    - Letters (re: work) of praise or rejection (Box 10, Folder 193)
    - Letters from E. J. Somerville, R. Buckminster Fuller, Hilton Edwards, Eleanor Roosevelt, John F. Kennedy, Archibald MacLeish, Wendell Wilkie, Carl Sandburg, and William Rose Benet, 1933-1975 (Box 10, Folder 194)
    - Letters to Maddie on 'The Wrong Man', to Peter [Hare] on religion..., 1961-1975, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 195)
    - [Letters from Larry Gates and postcard from Tom McDermott], 1963-1971 (Box 10, Folder 196)
    - [Correspondence] (Box 10, Folder 197)
    - [Correspondence] (Box 10, Folder 198)
- Personal files, Series V
  Scrapbooks
  - [Diary letters from Montgomery Hare to himself], 1961 (Box 10, Folder 199)
  - Christmas cards [painted by Montgomery Hare], 1972, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 200-201)
  - Journal, St. Lawrence boat trip, 1930 Aug (Box 10, Folder 202)
  - Journal, 1935-1945 (Box 10, Folder 203)
  - [Marriage vows booklet], 1908 (Box 11, Folder 204)
  - [Wedding photographs], 1908? (Box 11, Folder 205)
  - [Photographs of Mary Sturges (and others?)] (Box 11, Folder 206)
  - [Children's drawings] (Box 11, Folder 207)
  - Housatonic Valley Association, 1976-1980 (Box 11, Folder 208)
  - Housatonic Valley Association award, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 209)
  - [Charles Lindbergh documents], 1928, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 210)
  - [Blank stationary] (Box 11, Folder 211)
  - Copyrights (Box 11, Folder 212)
  - [Address cards] (Box 11, Folder 213-215)
  - [Address cards] (Box 11, Folder 216-222)
  - [Painting]
- Theater files, 1948-1952; Series VI
  - Barter Theatre, 1948-1952 (Box 11, Folder 223-224)
  - Barter Theatre, performed scripts (Box 12, Folder 225-226)
  - Playbills, some signed, 1949-1952 (Box 12, Folder 227)
  - [Playbills and photographs] (Box 12, Folder 228)
  - ["Thunderland" (directed by Montgomery Hare)], 1952 (Box 12, Folder 229-232)
  - Playbill for New Parsons Theatre (Box 12, Folder 233)
  - Actors' resumes (Box 12, Folder 234)
  - Engraving plate for tent theatre (Box 13, Folder 235)
  - Theatre notices, reviews (Box 13, Folder 236)
  - Parsons Theatre / Dramatronics, 1951-1953 (Box 13, Folder 237)
  - "Empire Theatre" (Box 13, Folder 238)
  - Penobscot Charitable Trust (Box 13, Folder 239)
  - [Penobscot Charitable Trust invitations] (Box 13, Folder 240-241)
  - [Penobscot Charitable Trust, "Towards Synergetic Theatre" cards] (Box 14)
- Other papers, 1937-1963; Series VII
  - [Material related to Richard Chase and miscellaneous documents], 1937-1963 (Box 15, Folder 242)
  - "Arts and Architecture" magazine, 1948 (Box 15, Folder 243)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15, Folder 244-250)
  - [Photographs] (Box 15, Folder 251)
  - [Photographs, rolled] (Box 16)
  - [Printed poem, rolled] (Box 16)
- Audiovisual Material, Series VIII
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Audiotape Reels
    - MH Flute, 1982 April; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888699)
      A written description of the contents are included.
      Bach Sonata IV in C major
      Telemann Fantasia #6 in F
      Mozart Andante
      Vivaldi Sonata #5
      Handel Sonata #VI
      Mozart Concerto #I in G
    - T[?] of Way, good tape with voice of MH..., undated; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888707)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888715)
    - "Ceremony", live recording, undated; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888723)
    - "Ceremony of Darkness", first copy, undated; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888731)
    - Navajo, undated; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888749)
    - 4 Poems with Autoharp, 1971 January; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888756)
    - "Manner of Navaho" - Prime, undated; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888764)
    - "White [?] with [?] Basche[?], 1971 February; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888772)
    - Poem to WHB and "Now in Nov.", 1971 January; 1 (Box 17, Item barcode 39002104888780)
    - Church Service, undated; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888798)
    - Church Service, undated; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888806)
      This may be a duplicate.
    - "Conscience and War" continued / Performance of "Tartuffe", New York, 1965, 1967 July 16; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888814)
    - "Conscience and War", a public forum discussion, 1967 July 16; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888822)
    - "The Game is Up", Wn. Hare, undated; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888830)
    - Side 1 - Fr. Joseph Cypriano, Address to Litchfield County Ministers / Side 2 - Rabbi Jerome R. Malino, "Religion & Creed", 1964 March 9, March 19; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888848)
    - "War and Conscience", undated; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888855)
    - "War and Conscience" I, undated; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888863)
    - Sides 1 + 2 - first tape Gould + Hare, undated; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888871)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 18, Item barcode 39002104888889)
    - Gould, Long, Hare and recap, undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889010)
    - Gould and Hare, after [?] evening, 1967 April 27; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889028)
    - Gould, Long, and Hare / Gould and Hare, 3rd reel, undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889036)
    - Cocktail Party Presentation, undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889044)
    - Drool about [?], undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889051)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889069)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889077)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889085)
    - Sound, Pianola..., undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889093)
    - added [?] ceremony, undated; 1 (Box 19, Item barcode 39002104889101)
    - "War and Conscience", undated; 1 (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104888970)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104888988)
    - Untitled, undated; 1 (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104888996)
    - WH flute, 1980; 1 (Box 20, Item barcode 39002104889002)
  - Audiocassettes
    - Gottschalk, undated; 1; 00:58:21; The program is distorted at times. (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888897)
    - Tape #2, undated; 1; 01:25:09 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888905)
      Written contents are included.
      "Say This of Me" - poem
      "Say This of Me" - little poem
      "Love Was"
      "Vernal Equinox"
      "Lament for a Bitch"
      "Eleanor"
      "Scrag 3"
      "Moment of Truth"
      "Small Song"
    - "Thoughts of Nature", 1989 August 25; 1; 01:14:37 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888913)
    - Poetry readings with commentary and flute, 1989 July; 1; 01:30:39 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888921)
      A typewritten list of contents is included.
      "Connie"
      "Mine Mountain"
      "Zen is a Bad Connection...", followed by Mozart on flute
      "Saga"
      "Nor Ships Nor Faces", with Corelli's Largo
      Vivaldi followed by "Mine to Kindle", commentary
      Lead into "Route 4, Goshen", first reading followed by Mozart
      "Route 4, Goshen", second reading with commentary
      "Moment of Truth", first reading and commentary
      "Moment of Truth", second reading and commentary
  - Audiocassettes, "Brecher Tapes"
    - Larry Gates and Montgomery Hare, tape 1 (1 of 2), 1992 January 22; 1; 01:35:19 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888939)
    - Larry Gates and Montgomery Hare, tape 2 (2 of 2), 1992 January 22; 1; 00:13:45 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888947)
    - Montgomery Hare and Larry Gates, tape 1 (1 of 2), 1992 February 4; 1; 01:36:35 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888954)
    - Montgomery Hare and Larry Gates, tape 2 (2 of 2), 1992 February 4; 1; 00:47:41 (Box 21, Item barcode 39002104888962)
  - Phonograph records, (8 records)
- Oversize
  - Scrapbook (in Series V) (Box 22)
  - Scrapbook (in Series V) (Box 23)
  - Poems with drawings (in Series I) (Box 23)
  - [Painting] (in Series V) (Box 24)
  - [Notebooks] (in Series II) (Box 24)
  - "To Beat the Air", original drawings (in Series I) (Box 24)
  - "Say This of Me", dummies, proofs, and original handwritten poems (in Series I) (Box 24)
  - "To Beat the Air", printing plates (in Series I) (Box 25)
- Record album storage
  - Phonograph records (in Series VIII) (Box 26 (Record album storage))
  - Phonograph records (in Series VIII) (Box 27 (Record album storage))